{
	"id": "FIN_PRA",
	"certName": "FINOPS Practitioner",
	"categories": [
		{
			"name": "Overview",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "what is FinOps?",
					"answer": "FinOps is an operational framework and cultural practice which maximizes the business value of cloud, enables timely data-driven decision making, and creates financial accountability through collaboration between engineering, finance, and business teams"
				}
			]
		},
		{
			"name": "Principles",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "Which are the 3 first principles of FinOps?",
					"answer": "1. Teams need to collaborate; 2. Decisions are driven by business value of cloud; 3. Everyone takes ownership of their cloud usage"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the 3 first principles of FinOps?",
					"answer": "4. FinOps data should be accessible and timely; 5. A centralized team drives FinOps; 6. Take advantage of the variable cost model of the cloud"
				}
			]
		},
		{
			"name": "Personas",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "What Personas represent?",
					"answer": "Broad stakeholder groups that must collaborate, not individual people"
				},
				{
					"question": "How Personas looks in a complex organization?",
					"answer": "A Persona may represent many people in various related roles"
				},
				{
					"question": "How Personas looks in a small organization?",
					"answer": "A single person may perfom the duties of multiple Personas"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the core Personas?",
					"answer": "1. FinOps practitioner; 2. Leadership; 3. Product; 4. Engineering; 5. Finance; 6. Procurement"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is the role of FinOps practitioner Persona?",
					"answer": "Bridge business, engineering, and finance teams by applying a working knowledge of the FinOps framework in order to establish a FinOps culture and enable evidence-based decisions to maximize the business value of cloud"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is the role of Leadership Persona?",
					"answer": "Empowers organizational alignment to prioritize FinOps initiatives, enables action to overcome FinOps challenges, and connects cloud technology decisions with business objectives"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is the role of Product Persona?",
					"answer": "Drive business value by defining requirements and prioritizing initiatives that align FinOps to business objectives, engaging stakeholders, and articulating the value-proposition of cloud technology decisiones"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is the role of Engineering Persona?",
					"answer": "Responsible for designing, managing and optimizing cloud infrastructure to achieve cost-effectiveness, performance, reliability while ensuring the security and compliance of cloud environments"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is the role of Finance Persona?",
					"answer": "Provides financial expertise and works closely with FinOps Practitioners to reconcile cloud provider invoices with cloud billing data to accurately forecast, budget and chargeback cloud costs"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is the role of Procurement Persona?",
					"answer": "Responsible for procuring cloud services, optimizing vendor relationships, and ensuring cost-effective and compliant vendor engagements, collaborating with FinOps Practitioners to ensure rates contribute to the successful management of cloud finances"
				},
				{
					"question": "What are Allied Personas?",
					"answer": "Roles that are not directly involved in the practice of FinOps but has intersecting disciplines"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the Allied Personas?",
					"answer": "1. ITSM/ITIL; 2. ITAM; 3. Sustainability; 4. Security; 5. ITFM"
				},
				{
					"question": "What ITSM/ITIL stands for?",
					"answer": "IT Service Management"
				},
				{
					"question": "What ITAM stands for?",
					"answer": "IT Asset Management"
				},
				{
					"question": "What ITFM stands for?",
					"answer": "IT Financial Management"
				}
			]
		},
		{
			"name": "Phases",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "Which are the FinOps phases?",
					"answer": "1. Inform; 2. Optimize; 3. Operate"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is Inform phase about?",
					"answer": "Visibility and allocation; Identifying data sources for cloud cost, usage and efficiency data"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is Optimize phase about?",
					"answer": "Rates and usage; Identifying opportunities to improve cloud efficiency using the data and capabilities"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is Operate phase about?",
					"answer": "Continuous improvement and usage; Establishing cloud governance policies, compliance monitoring, and empowering individuals through the development of training programs, team guidelines, and automation policies that are aligned with organizational objectives"
				}
			]
		},
		{
			"name": "Maturity model",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "Which elements are evaluated with the maturity model?",
					"answer": "Maturity model is applied to evaluate capabilities and domains"
				},
				{
					"question": "If we want to evolve a capability or domain, which one should we prioritize?",
					"answer": "We should prioritize those who gives the most business value"
				},
				{
					"question": "If we want to evolve a capability or domain, which one should we prioritize?",
					"answer": "We should prioritize those who gives the most business value"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the stages of the maturity model?",
					"answer": "1. Crawl; 2. Walk; 3. Run"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the first 2 characteristics of Crawl stage of the maturity model?",
					"answer": "1. Very little reporting and tooling; 2. Measurements only provide insight into the benefits of maturing this capability"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the second 2 characteristics of Crawl stage of the maturity model?",
					"answer": "3. Basic KPIs set for the measurement of success; 4. Basic processes and policies are defined around the capability"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the third 2 characteristics of Crawl stage of the maturity model?",
					"answer": "5. Capability is understood but not followed by all major teams within the organization; 6. Plans to address the 'low hanging fruit'"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the first 2 characteristics of Walk stage of the maturity model?",
					"answer": "1. Capability is understood and followed within the organization; 2. Difficult edge cases are identified but decision to not address them is adopted"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the second 2 characteristics of Walk stage of the maturity model?",
					"answer": "3. Automation and/or processes cover most of the Capability requirements; 4. Most difficult edge cases (ones that threaten the financial well-being of the organization) are identified and effort to resolve has been estimated"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the third 2 characteristics of Walk stage of the maturity model?",
					"answer": "5. Medium to high goals/KPIs set on the measurement of success"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the first 2 characteristics of Run stage of the maturity model?",
					"answer": "1. Capability is understood and followed by all teams within the organization; 2. Difficult edge cases are being addressed"
				},
				{
					"question": "Which are the second 2 characteristics of Run stage of the maturity model?",
					"answer": "3. Very high goals/KPIs set on the measurement of success; 4. Automation is the preferred approach"
				}
			]
		},
		{
			"name": "Understanding Cloud Usage & Cost Domain",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "What is the target of Understanding Cloud usage and cost domain?",
					"answer": "Better understanding of an organization's use of the cloud"
				},
				{
					"question": "What capabilities are associated with Optimize Cloud usage and cost domain?",
					"answer": "1. Data ingestion; 2. Allocation; 3. Reporting and analytics; 4. Anomaly management"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is enabled by this domain?",
					"answer": "It enables an organization to understand what cloud services it's using, what is driving spend, and who is responsible for that spend"
				}
			]
		},
		{
			"name": "Optimize Cloud Usage & Cost Domain",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "What is the target of Optimize Cloud usage and cost domain?",
					"answer": "Cloud efficiency by designing and building systems effectively, reducing waste and unnecessary usage over time, and optimizing rates paid for needed resources"
				},
				{
					"question": "What capabilities are associated with Optimize Cloud usage and cost domain?",
					"answer": "1. Architecting for cloud; 2. Rate optimization; 3. Workload optimization; 4. Cloud sustainability; 5. Licensing and SaaS"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is ensured by this domain?",
					"answer": "It ensures organizations use resources only when and where they provide the most value to the organization"
				}
			]
		},
		{
			"name": "Shared costs",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "Which are the three common methods for splitting up shared costs",
					"answer": "1. Even split; 2. Fixed proportional; 3. Variable proportional"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is even split shared cost about",
					"answer": "Split total amount evenly across targets"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is fixed proportional shared cost about",
					"answer": "Based on relative percentage of costs, usage, or some other metric which is infrequently updated"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is variable proportional shared cost about",
					"answer": "Based on relative percentage of costs, usage, or some other metric which is routinely used for determining the split of spend"
				}
			]
		},
		{
			"name": "FinOps adoption",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "How FinOps adoption begins?",
					"answer": "1. Leadership mandate; 2. Grassroots adoption; 3. Individual initiative"
				},
				{
					"question": "What are the typical stages of FinOps adoption?",
					"answer": "1. Research; 2. Propose; 3. Prepare; 4. Launch"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is Research stage of FinOps adoption about?",
					"answer": "It is about collecting the inputs for your FinOps adoption proposal"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is Propose stage of FinOps adoption about?",
					"answer": "It is about bring other members of your organization on board with implementing FinOps practice"
				},
				{
					"question": "How do we define the opportunity in the Propose stage of FinOps adoption?",
					"answer": "You have to paint a picture of: 1. the current state; 2. a roadmap of FinOps activities; and 3. an appealing future with FinOps"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is Prepare stage of FinOps adoption about?",
					"answer": "It is about preparing to execute against those approved plans"
				},
				{
					"question": "What is Launch stage of FinOps adoption about?",
					"answer": "It is about implementing the designed processes, tools and policies"
				}
			]
		},
		{
			"name": "Domains",
			"questions": [
				{
					"question": "Which are the FinOps domains?",
					"answer": "1. Understanding cloud usage and costs; 2. Quantify business value; 3. Optimize cloud usage and costs; 4. Manage the FinOps practice"
				}
			]
		}
	]
}